Okay, I'm back.
In this series of videos,
we're gonna cover customization of the shell,
multiple sessions support, scripts, race execs,
batch support, and translation issues.
A shell user has several options to personalize the shell.
A user can create their own .profile file
where user variables are defined to do things like
point to a log on script or define a search path
to be used when locating a file or a directory
and identify the editor to be used.
Environment variables can be defined in the login script.
The login script is started each time a shell is started.
The login script can contain all alias definitions
and other setup instructions.
By using the set command,
the user can set options for the shell session.
These options control the way
the shell handles certain situations.
When the shell is invoked as a login shell,
.etc, .profile, and .home, .profile are used.
If users want environment variables
in a shell invoked from the current shell,
they should identify a file in an env environment variable
and place shell commands in the file.
The system interprets the file named in env
each time a new shell is invoked.
Depending on the commands used to set it,
an environment variable can be local,
meaning it's used only for the current process
or exported, used for the current process
and for any other processes spawned by the current process.
There are many environment variables
set for your shell session,
and if requested, they're available to all commands
or all programs that the shell runs as child processes.
Variables like log name, home, and shell
are set for you by RACF
when you're validated as a user of the system.
Others like lock path, lib path, and man path
are lists of directories, search for locales,
dynamic load libraries, and online documentation pages.
The example shown here is from slash samples slash profile.
All shell users get the environment variables
set by this profile.
Users can override some of the variables
by setting the variables in their private profiles
or in their shell sessions.
Note that all environment variables
are written with uppercase letters,
and the contents of slash etc slash profile
are actually a shell script.
It contains examples of the script programming languages
with if then statements.
It sets values for environment variables
and it issues some shell commands
like export, Umask, and read only.
Any changes made in slash etc slash profile
will take effect the next time
a user invokes the shell.
Here we see three methods that shell users can use
to customize the environment variables for their shell.
They can all be used,
but the last setting will take precedence.
First up, the dollar home slash dot profile file.
A sample is provided in slash samples slash dot profile,
which can be copied
to a shell user's home directory and modified.
The env variable in the dollar home slash dot profile file
can be set to a file name,
which is a shell script that sets environment variables.
Shell users can use the env command
to display the environment variables for their session
and to change any of these variables.
The change only lasts for the length of the session.
If you use the omvs command to log into the shell,
you can improve performance
by using a log on procedure
that does not contain any job lib or step lib dd allocations.
This reduces the amount of storage that is copied for fork.
It also prevents extensive searching of step live datasets
and the propagation of step live datasets
from the shell process
to the shell command process on exec.
Statements in either the slash etc slash profile
or dollar home slash dot profile files as shown here,
improve the shell's performance for users
who enter the omvs command from ISPF
or with step live datasets allocated.
We'll continue to look at the shell in the next video,
starting with multi session support.